Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley papers
1879-1984
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brinley, Daniel Putnam
14.3 linear feet
The papers of painter and muralist Daniel Putnam Brinley and his wife, linguist and writer Kathrine Sanger Brinley, date from 1879 to 1984 and measure 14.3 linear feet. The Brinleys' careers and lives are documented in biographical materials, as well as extensive correspondence with one another, family, friends, art galleries, organizations, publishers, and others. Also found within the papers are writings by both, including 16 diaries (1 by Daniel Putnam Brinley and the rest by Kathrine), essays, manuscripts, typescripts, notes and notebooks, poetry, and various other writings. There are mural commission files, files for organizations of which the Brinleys were members, financial and legal records, exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material. Also found are photographs of the Brinleys, family, friends, travels, and artwork, and six sketchbooks and original artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley.
Provenance
The Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley papers were lent for microfilming by their niece, Elizabeth Loder, in 1978-1979. Loder subsequently donated all but select family photographs in 1991 and additional material in 1992.
Separated Material
Originals of loaned material, including family photographs, were returned to Elizabeth Loder after microfilming. Loaned material is available on reel 1427 but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art is the Elizabeth Loder research material on Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1919-1990.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of this collection was digitized in 2009 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Material not scanned includes routine financial records, a portion of the printed material, and photographs of works of art.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Daniel Putnam Brinley (1879-1963) was a muralist and painter in New York City and New Canaan, Connecticut. Brinley was born in Newport, Rhode Island, and studied from 1900 to 1902 at the Art Student's League under Kenyon Cox and John Henry Twachtman. Influenced by Twachtman, he became an impressionist landscape painter for a time. In 1904, he married his childhood friend, writer Kathrine Gordon Sanger (1877-1966). For the next four years they traveled throughout Europe and lived in Paris, where Brinley studied art independently and became a member of the modernist circle of painters.
In 1908 the Brinleys returned to the United States and Daniel established a studio in New York City. During this period his work was heavily influenced by the modernist movement, with flattened forms and a deeper hued palette. Brinley had his first one-man show at Madison Avenue Galleries in 1910, exhibited at Alfred Stieglitz's gallery at 291, and helped organized the 1913 Armory Show. He was also a founding member of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors and the Grand Central Art Galleries. In 1914 the Brinleys built a home, Datchet House, in New Canaan, Connecticut, and spent part of each year there for the remainder of their lives.
In 1917 Daniel Putnam Brinley trained with the American Expeditionary Forces and went to France as the Director of Decoration for the Foyers Du Soldat (YMCA), remaining there until 1919. After returning to the United States he became a mural painter and received numerous commissions for memorials, office buildings, churches, and public spaces over the next forty years. Perhaps most notable of these commissions was the Liberty War Memorial in Kansas City, Missouri, for which Brinley painted 24 decorative maps showing the history of World War I. He remained active in the art community as a member of the Architectural League of New York, the National Academy of Design, and the Silvermine Guild of Artists, among others.
Kathrine Sanger Brinley was a writer and linguist who worked in Europe, New York City, and Connecticut. She lived in Europe from 1904 to 1908 where she studied the arts and crafts of the middle ages and became an expert on English writing and language of the 14th century. She published articles and books on these subjects and during the 1920s had a successful career touring as a dramatic recitalist of the works of Geoffrey Chaucer. From 1934 to 1938 the Brinley's spent their summers traveling throughout Canada, and Kathrine published four travel books which were illustrated by Daniel Putnam Brinley. Kathrine Sanger Brinley published and wrote professionally under the name Gordon Brinley.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and muralist Daniel Putnam Brinley and his wife, linguist and writer Kathrine Sanger Brinley, date from 1879 to 1984 and measure 14.3 linear feet. The Brinleys' careers and lives are documented in biographical materials, as well as extensive correspondence with one another, family, friends, art galleries, organizations, publishers, and others. Also found within the papers are writings by both, including 16 diaries (1 by Daniel Putnam Brinley and the rest by Kathrine), essays, manuscripts, typescripts, notes and notebooks, poetry, and various other writings. There are mural commission files, files for organizations of which the Brinleys were members, financial and legal records, exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material. Also found are photographs of the Brinleys, family, friends, travels, and artwork, and six sketchbooks and original artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley.
Biographical material consists of biographical sketches and professional summaries for both Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, passports, personal mementos, award certificates, two radio interview transcripts, and military records documenting Daniel Putnam Brinley's service in the American Expeditionary Forces and the Camouflage Corps.
The papers contain extensive correspondence (4.6 linear feet) divided into family correspondence and general correspondence. Family correspondence includes letters between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley and with their parents and siblings. General correspondence primarily includes the Brinley's personal correspondence with friends and extended family. These letters discuss travel, mutual acquaintances, social events, and general news. Also found is professional correspondence regarding the exhibition and commission of artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley and the publication of writings by Kathrine Sanger Brinley. Also discussed in the letters are the Brinleys' participation in art, social, and religious organizations. Correspondence of note is with Edwin Blashfield, Edward Bruce, William A. Coffin, Charles H. Davis, John Erskine, Anthony Euwer, Esperanza Gabay, Robert Henri, Hildreth Meiere, Ernest Peixotto, and Hugh Troy.
Writings and notes are by Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley. Included among their writings are one diary by Daniel Putnam Brinley, 15 diaries by Kathrine Sanger Brinley, essays, notebooks and notes, manuscripts, and typescripts. Subjects of their writings include essays about religion, poetry, and autobiographical and travel essays. Also found among Daniel Putnam Brinley's writing are lecture notes, fictional stories and plays, essays about art, and historical research for his mural projects.
Mural commission files include correspondence, lists, contracts, financial agreements, notes, plans, sketches, and photographs for specific murals. There is extensive documentation on murals Brinley completed for the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company in New York and the Liberty War Memorial in Kansas City Missouri. Organization files document the Brinleys' participation in art and social organizations.
Scattered financial and legal records include receipts, account books, leases, estate and power of attorney documents, and records regarding their house and property in New Canaan, Connecticut. Printed material consists of published items documenting the careers, social activities and personal interest of the Brinleys, and includes books, exhibition catalogs and announcements, news clippings, newsletters, and items from their travels abroad.
Photographs depict Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, individually and with family and friends, and include photographs of Daniel Putnam Brinley working on mural commissions. Also found are photographs of their travels, their homes, Daniel Putnam Brinley's artwork, and reference photographs for his murals. Artwork in this collection includes six of Daniel Putnam Brinley's sketchbooks, primarily from his travels in Europe and Canada, loose drawings and mural studies, drawings by Albert Sterner and Reinhold Palenske, and a lithograph by John Steuart Curry.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1879-1970s (Box 1, OV 16; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1879-1984 (Box 1-6; 4.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1895-1964 (Box 6-9; 3.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Commission Files, 1920-1979 (Box 9-10; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Organization Files, 1909-1964 (Box 10-11; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 6: Financial and Legal Records, 1896-1965 (Box 11; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1895-1979 (Box 11-13, OV 16-17; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1881-1971 (Box 13-14, OV 22; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1891-1950s (Box 14-15, OVs 18-21; 0.9 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Muralists--Connecticut--New Canaan; Mural painting and decoration--United States; Painters--Connecticut--New Canaan; Authors--Connecticut--New Canaan
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Photographs; Poetry; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Works of art; Writings
Names:
Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1848-1936; Brinley, Kathrine Sanger; Bruce, Edward, 1879-1943; Coffin, William A. (William Anderson), 1855-1925; Davis, Charles H. (Charles Harold), 1856-1933; Erskine, John, 1879-1951; Euwer, Anthony; Gabay, Esperanza; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Meiere, M. Hildreth, d. 1961; Peixotto, Ernest, b. 1869; Troy, Hugh
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1879-1970s, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 16; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series contains biographical documents for both Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, including obituaries, handwritten and typed biographical sketches, chronologies, and biographical entries for Who's Who publications. Also found are two questionnaires from unidentified organizations, lists of artwork by Daniel Putnam Brinley, and several award certificates. This series also includes official documents such as passports and their marriage certificate, as well as personal mementos and items from their childhood, such as school records and a handwritten account of Brinley's birth by his mother. Other items of note are early versions of Daniel Putnam Brinley's will and records of his military service in the American Expeditionary Forces and the Camouflage Corps. There are two radio interview transcripts, including a 1942 interview of Kathrine Sanger Brinley and a 1945 interview of both Daniel and Kathrine Brinley.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Admission tickets have not been scanned.
  - Obituaries for Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituaries for Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Sketches & Chronologies, Daniel Putnam Brinley, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Sketches, Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Who's Who Biographical Sketches, Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1935-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Who's Who Biographical Sketches, Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Questionnaires, circa early-1900, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Artwork, circa 1919, 1938, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Brinley Family History, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Award Certificates, 1904, 1913-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passports, 1926-1927, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership Cards, 1901-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Birth Record for Daniel Putnam Brinley (Written by Mother), 1879 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lock of Daniel Putnam Brinley's Hair, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Church Certificates, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kathrine & Emma Sanger School Records, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Miscellaneous Items found in Wallet of Wm. I. Sanger", circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Last Will and Testament, Daniel Putnam Brinley, 1904, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wedding Announcement, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1904, (Oversized, housed in OV 16) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annotated List of First Class Passengers, S. S. Minneapolis, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Autographed Salamagundi Club Menu, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Camouflage Corps Records, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Expeditionary Forces-YMCA Records, 1917-1923, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - Map of Brinley Property, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Information on Books by Kathrine Sanger "Gordon" Brinley, 1934-circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Radio Interview, Station WSRR Stamford, April 27, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Radio Interview, D. M. Read Company, January 18, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Armory Show 50th Anniversary Exhibition Materials, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Personal Mementos, Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Address Books, circa 1908-1950s, (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-39)
  - Calling Cards, circa early-1900s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Admission Tickets, 1904-1964, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, circa 1920s-1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1904, (From Box 1, F20) (Box OV 16)
- Correspondence, 1879-1984, Series 2:; (Box 1-6; 4.6 linear feet)
  Correspondence includes family correspondence and general correspondence. Family correspondence is primarily between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, and with immediate family. Letters discuss their travels in Europe, Daniel Putnam Brinley's military service, and other family news.
  General Correspondence includes the Brinleys' personal correspondence with friends and extended family and professional correspondence. Correspondence of note is with artists Edwin Blashfield, Edward Bruce, William A. Coffin, Charles H. Davis, Anthony Euwer, Esperanza Gabay, Robert Henri, Hildreth Meiere, Ernest Peixotto, Hugh Troy, and writer John Erskine.
  The Correspondence series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 2.1: Family Correspondence, 1879-1940s, 1971
  Subseries 2.2: General Correspondence, circa 1888-1984
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically. The material has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Family Correspondence, 1879-1940s, 1971, Subseries 2.1:
    Much of the family correspondence is between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley during the periods that they were apart, especially the period before their marriage in 1904 and during the time that Daniel Putnam Brinley was in the American Expeditionary Forces in France from 1917 to 1919. These intimate, detailed letters discuss their travels and events in their everyday lives. Researchers should note that the Brinleys often addressed each other with nicknames such as "Jock" or "Put" for Daniel Putnam Briley, and "Kat" or "Dee Dee" for Kathrine Sanger Brinley. Also found are transcripts and partial transcripts of some of these letters. Additional family correspondence is between Kathrine Sanger Brinley and her sister Emma Sanger, often called "Gippie", "Gyppie", or "Gip", correspondence with her brother William Sanger, her parents William and Kate, and correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and his mother. Within these letters the family discusses their travels, including the Brinley's extensive travels throughout Europe, and news of acquaintances and events. Also found here are a few of Elizabeth Loder's notes on the family correspondence.
    - Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1899-1904, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-51)
    - Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1908-1917, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    - Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1918, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 8-12)
    - Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1919, 1921-1942, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    - Undated Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Transcripts of Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1900-1901, 1918-1919, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence with Emma "Gippie" Sanger (Sister of Kathrine Sanger Brinley), 1896-1945, (12 folders) (Box 2, Folder 19-30)
    - Correspondence with William Sanger (Brother of Kathrine Sanger Brinley), 1896-1932, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
    - Correspondence with William and Kate Sanger (Parents of Kathrine Sanger Brinley), 1895-1926, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-37)
    - Correspondence between Daniel Putnam Brinley and his Mother, 1904-1906, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters to the Parents of Daniel Putnam Brinley regarding his Birth, March 1879 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes about Family Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, circa 1888-1984, Subseries 2.2:
    General correspondence includes Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley's personal and professional correspondence, mostly incoming letters, for a period of over 75 years. The bulk of the letters are from friends and extended family and discuss travel, mutual acquaintances, social events, and other general news. Much of the personal correspondence does not include the sender's last name. Also found are many letters from Katherine's former priest, E. A. Bazett-Jones, who often addressed her as "daughter" in his letters, and other members the religious community in which the Brinley's were active members.
    Professional correspondence discusses Daniel Putnam Brinley's art exhibitions, mural and painting commissions, the sale of his artwork, and his involvement in art organizations and events. Also included is Kathrine Sanger Brinley's correspondence with magazine and book publishers such as Craftsman magazine and Dodd, Mead & Company, regarding the publishing of her articles and travel books. The Brinley's maintained very little correspondence with other artists, but notable correspondents include the artists William Chadwick, Anthony Euwer, Charles H. Davis, Edward Bruce, Esperanza Gabay, Robert Henri (one letter, dated 1914), Hildreth Meiere, Edwin Blashfield, William A. Coffin, Ernest Peixotto, and Hugh Troy, as well as the writer John Erskine. This subseries also includes a small amount of Elizabeth Loder's correspondence with art organizations, galleries, and others regarding the Brinleys.
    Researchers should note that additional correspondence can be found in Series 4: Commission Files and Series 5: Organization Files.
    - Correspondence, circa 1888-1904, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-10)
    - Correspondence, 1905-1915, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-17)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1925, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 18-24)
    - Correspondence, 1926-1931, (11 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-35)
    - Correspondence, 1932-1935, (11 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1939, (9 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-20)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1942, (7 folders) (Box 4, Folder 21-27)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1946, (8 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1955, (11 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-19)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1962, (8 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-27)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1965, (8 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    - Unidentified Correspondence, circa 1900-1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Undated Correspondence, circa 1900-1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Elizabeth Loder Correspondence regarding Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley, 1965-1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1895-1964, Series 3:; (Box 6-9; 3.3 linear feet)
  Writings and notes are by both Daniel Putnam Brinley and Kathrine Sanger Brinley. These include one diary of Daniel's and fifteen of Kathrine's. There are also numerous notebooks, essays, prose, lecture notes, research notes, travel essays, notes about religion, autobiographical essays, and poetry. Among Kathrine Sanger Brinley's writings are numerous engagement calendars.
  The Writings and Notes series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Writings and Notes by Daniel Putnam Brinley, circa early 1900s-1962
  Subseries 3.2: Writings and Notes by Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1895-1964
  Writings have been loosely grouped by type, format, and subjects. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Writings and Notes by Daniel Putnam Brinley, circa early 1900s-1962, Subseries 3.1:
    There is one diary kept by Daniel Putnam Brinley while he was traveling to Paris in 1918 to work for the American Expeditionary Forces. Also found with the diary are transcripts and summaries of portions of the diary. Three notebooks include essays about his participation in the Foyers du Soldat, about religious art, and a fictional story called "Nightmare." There are additional essays about art and his travels in Canada. Also found are short stories, research notes for his murals, poetry, plays, lecture notes, autobiographical accounts, and miscellaneous notes. One item, "A Trip to Mount Washington," is illustrated.
    - Diary, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Notebook, "Decorating a Foyer in Montdidier", 1918 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Notebook, "Religious Art", circa 1914 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Notebook, "Nightmare", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Writings about Travels in Canada, circa 1934 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "Color in Relation to Art and Life", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Mr. Rubenstine", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "Now Listen Children Before You Sleep", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Preamble", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Scoop", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - "Subject Matter for a Pictorial Presentation of the Opening and Development of the West", circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "The Awakening of Emma: A Comedy in One Act", circa 1908 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - "Decorating a foyer in Montdidier", 1918 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - "A Ballad of Marriage: To Cornelia and Hildie", 1922 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - "The Queen Anne Shop - Bermuda", circa 1920s (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - "Talk given at St. Mark's in the Bowerie", 1936 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - "A Trip to Mount Washington by Uncle Dan and the Duchess", 1936 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - "The Dumb Wife or Murder in the Air", circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "Newport, R. I.", 1954 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - "I Call This a Crazy Tale", 1958 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - "Put's Speech re: Armory Show", circa 1962 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Engagement Calendar, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1900s-1950s, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 34-35)
  - Writings and Notes by Kathrine Sanger Brinley, circa 1895-1964, Subseries 3.2: